In the US, [music]
if you put in a request for a hundreds
of megawatts of power to build the data
center today, good luck getting that
power before 2031. That's the situation
that we have today. So, new technologies
like sodium ion batteries could drop the
cost of batteries by a factor of 10. We
already have [music] the very first
solar plus battery load power plants and
they're affordable. batteries are
plunging in cost and are going to drop
another 10x ultimately.
>> Do you believe that thesis that solar in
the [music] long term is going to
dominate beyond everything else?
>> The reality is look, everybody's heard
Elon [music] talking about space-based
data centers. So 10 gawatt a year is
like five or six launches of Starship a
day.
>> Unless we hit that exponential
absolutely fullon and go right down that
[music] path, this looks prohibitive for
15 20 years. The biggest unlock that we
cannot predict of [music] AI and power
will be.
>> Now that's a moonshot, ladies and
gentlemen.
>> Everybody, welcome to Moonshot. Another
episode on the front line of the
singularity. We're living during the
most extraordinary time ever. And our
mission here is to deliver you the
breaking news and help you understand
what's going on. Today we're going to be
doing a deep dive into the innermost
loop, all things energy. I'm here with
my extraordinary moonshot mates, uh,
DB2, AWG, Salem. Welcome, gentlemen.
Good to see you all. Looks like you're
normal haunts. And we've got a friend
with us today. Everybody on Moonshots,
it is an honor and a pleasure uh for us
to invite Rome Nam. Uh Romez is uh a
computer scientist, investor, author,
one of the clearest thinkers on the
future of energy. After a career at
Microsoft, Rome became the leading voice
in the exponential decline in the cost
of solar, batteries, fision, fusion. Uh
he's the founder, managing partner of
Planetary VC, investing in energy
companies. He's the author of the
infinite resource and one of my favorite
ever science fiction novel series, the
Nexus trilogy. If you've not read Nexus,
uh, I cannot commend it. On Book Corner,
where Alex and I talk about our books,
I've mentioned Nexus a few times. Today,
we're going to be exploring the
innermost loop, uh, why energy abundance
may arrive faster than most forecast,
and its impact on AI, economic growth,
geopolitics, and our future. Again, my
mission here is at the end of this
podcast uh and the brilliant dialogue
that my moonshot mates is going to bring
to the table here uh you're going to
understand either if you're an investor,
if you're a builder, what's the alpha?
Where is it going? Uh what are the real
timelines for everything from building
out nuclear plants, fusion plants, uh
because you know, sometimes there's
hype, sometimes there is an overwhelming
abundance of energy coming our way. So,
first off, Hermes, welcome pal.
>> Peter, it's an honor to be here. Great
to be here with friends. Look forward to
it.
>> You do have friends here. So, uh, uh,
you know,
>> I have a I have a quick story.
>> Yeah, of course you have a story.
[laughter]
>> I'm worried.
>> I remember, uh, we were we were
presenting to one of the top oil
companies and energy companies in the
world, like top three or four, and they
were like, well, who's this Rome fellow?
uh we want to grill him before we let
him in front of the the key people here.
We're like fine, grill Romez. And so the
because we were talking a lot about
solar and they're an oil and gas company
and after like 2 hours they're like okay
we need to get in front of them.
[laughter] That was it. It was an
awesome session.
>> Yeah. One thing I failed to mention is
uh Rome was part of our founding faculty
at Singular University. Uh really led
the whole energy uh conversation there
and has been on stage at the Abundant
Summit number of times. Hopefully you're
back again coming in 2027. Uh Mez, uh uh
first of all, I just need to try you.
You need to write a fourth, fifth, and
sixth [laughter]
trilogy.
>> As soon as AI and energy get less
exciting every single week, I will make
time to write another novel.
>> How much time do you spend tracking
what's going on on the innermost loop
here?
>> It's every day, all day. I mean, that's
what we all do, right? Living in the
singularity. Yeah, we this is living the
singularity. Before we get jumping in,
Alex, you want to add anything to the
conversation up front?
>> I I'll just add welcome to the terror
dome. One of my my my favorite of of
your I would say popularizations that
now infamous chart of the price of solar
going down to zero.
>> Thank you, Alex.
>> Uh amazing. Well, uh I can't take
another second away from you, pal. uh
jump on in and we'll grill you along the
way, make the points, you know, uh you
know, shall we say, in a stellar
fashion. Okay,
>> great. Let's just start. We're going to
hit a few different topics here with the
intersection of electricity, really
energy and compute. I mean, a few years
ago as an investor in clean energy, that
was sort of a uh a fringe sector to some
people, though it's $3 trillion. uh but
now that we see that AI depends upon
electricity it is everything like the
you know capital flows value flows to
that which is scarce and right now power
is scarce so we're going six topics at
the end of each we're going to pause to
have discussion so number one AI is
power hungry two speed to power and the
grid that's everything it's not cost
three behind the meter power that's how
it's happening four making the grid
better is totally undervalue value and
that's where the near-term wins are.
Five, solar. Six, vision and fusion.
Lots of stuff happening. And seven,
finally, uh the out of this world ideas,
launching uh compute into space or
launching it into the oceans. So, let's
just cement ourselves on AI as power
hungry. You have to exponentially
increase compute to get linear gains in
AI. There are some ways to cheat that
curve which we're doing but that's the
basic uh phenomenon here and I think we
don't fully gro most people anyway the
relationship between these things. First
I want to be clear that power is cheap
compared to GPUs. So if you look at
building a gigawatt data center you're
going to spend $50 billion 35 billion of
that for chips. When you compare the
ratio of like the allup capex of your
data center to your five-year energy
cost, it is amazing how little energy
costs. So when you say AI is power
hungry, it's not really a cost issue. It
is that energy is the bottleneck for AI.
And this has a lot of ramifications
because these numbers are in billions or
tens of billions of dollars. Every
hyperscaler has whole teams devoted to
optimizing the cost of energy. But if
you tell Open AI or Anthropic today,
look, we can give you power at twice the
cost that's on tomorrow, uh, they'll
take it. They they won't tell you that
of course, but they will take it because
the revenue you can generate from a unit
of electricity to the cost of it is
basically the same ratio as this. So
what's the challenge? The challenge is
uh we stopped being able to build out
the grid fast. And I'm not talking about
power generation. We can still do that
pretty fast at least for solar, wind,
batteries, and natural gas. But the
poles and wires are a huge problem. So
this is uh we talk about the
interconnection queue which is the cue
to get your uh new project hooked up to
the grid and this is for the generation
side. If you're building a new solar
plant, wind plant, natural gas plant,
how long does it take before you are
hooked up to the grid so you can deliver
power to your customers? that's gone
from 15 months 20 years ago to now
coming up on 45 months.
>> Regulations, what is it?
>> It's regulation and it's also that as
demand has demand growth has slowed,
right? The US uh demand growth per year
is much slower than it was the 80s even
let alone the 50s. Uh utilities have
just you re-engineered themselves. they
are more oriented on uh customer service
on meeting the regulators demands and so
on than they are on building stuff fast.
So that has got in the way. But
permitting is also a huge issue. Not
utility regulation per se, but
permitting issues for the land
controlled by the state, the county, the
feds.
>> If we're if we're just going to jump in
uh led led by Peter's example, I have to
ask you you sort of flew by. You you
mentioned or you alluded to this notion
that intelligence was somehow
proportional to log compute which I I
know a number of executives have have
also pushed the the narrative of maybe
you could one could naively extrapolate
some law that looked like that from
scaling laws uh in in machine learning
training or machine learning inference.
Do you think that's actually true? And
if you do think it's true, do you think
it continues to be true in an epic of
recursive self-improvement?
It's an awesome question, Alex, and this
is like core to the like the big
questions of AI and are we going to have
a recursive self-improvement to ASI? Uh,
look, everything in machine learning
like since 2000 has shown something like
a log linear relationship between really
between training data size and precision
of a model. Right. My you're alluding I
I think to first Kaplan scaling and then
chinchilla scaling and then post
chinchilla scaling. long before
chinchilla scaling with single layer
neural nets. We were finding this in the
early 2000s, right? So
compute is used to convert training data
into a model, right? Into a neural
network and uh that has a roughly log
linear relationship, but we cheat and by
which I mean we keep finding ways to
make that more efficient. So is it
actually log linear? No, it's a little
bit faster than that because we keep
finding ways as we see with Deepseek
Flash that just came out as we see with
Kimmy K3. We keep finding ways to bend
that curve. So, it's a little bit less
bad than log linear, but it's still it's
somewhere between a power law like n to
the fifth uh and a true exponential or
log uh scale difficulty. uh and I don't
see that changing uh anytime soon.
>> This seems it seems almost if I
understand your broader thesis, this
seems almost axiomatic that if we can't
bend the the log curve that that we need
basically exponentially larger amounts
of energy just to make essentially
linear or polomial progress in
intelligence. We need more and more
energy. We need to uh achieve
Cardartesev level two or Cardartesev
level three type civilization Dyson
swarms in order just to keep making
incremental progress past [laughter]
right like this
>> is getting at the Alex is getting at the
core issue with with super intelligence
actually in a certain extent look like
here's my view Alex like the naive view
is at any given time intelligence is
basically log linear with compute log
linear with data but we keep making the
algorithms better and that sneaks us
towards like a polomial domain but the
polomial domain is still steeply
diminishing returns you're arguing it's
poly log you're arguing that
intelligence is poly log in compute
>> at best it's polomial and I don't not
necessarily poly log but at best I mean
we see like the very best examples you
can get is maybe uh compute has to go up
uh you know n to the fourth to get an n
size increase in intelligence
>> and you don't think recursive self
improvement if we are indeed in an era
of RSI. You don't think that causes
anything better than poly log?
>> No. Look, you do the math on RSI and
RSI, every way that you improve AI has
diminishing returns. So, every model of
RSI that does not include hardware, we
can save that. Every model of RSI and
software fizzles over time. Now, the
bump might be so big that we're like,
wow, this is just over the top amazing,
but it it always looks concave. There is
no mathematical model of RSI that's
valid that I can see that leads to an
actual like, you know, vertical asmtote
take off. This episode is sponsored by
Google for startups. Think about this
for a second. You now have access to the
same generative AI models that cost
hundreds of millions of dollars to
train. Google's startup technical
[music] guide for generative media gives
you complete blueprint for deploying
Google deep minds models in production
[music] images video audio all of it
real architecture real results find the
link in the show notes below
I'm going to take us back so the grid is
the grid [laughter]
>> the grid is the bottleneck right now
>> yes it is so we need power in a
practical sense look everybody
>> and Alex Not that I did not appreciate
your genius in those questions and that
was fun. And this may turn out to be an
entire conversation between Rome and
Alex, but we'll see.
>> Let's have another way to talk about
that.
>> I got words to I got words. Um
[laughter]
I think I think I think the the point
here is the grid is the bottleneck is a
really important point because it speaks
to the infrastructure needs we're going
to have to have for dealing with this.
So let's move on. We'll get I'll come
back to it. And look, so this is for the
power side. For the demand side, we
don't have data that is as clean. But
here are like three locations around the
US. And you see in this 7month period
between April and November last year,
the wait times to get connected for the
load side, not for generation, but for
your data center, whatnot, went up by
six, seven months. So everywhere around
the country uh as demand is going up for
large load interconnection uh you're
seeing longer and longer weight. So this
is Texas is a Texas grid. Uh Urkot
currently it peaks out at about 80
gawatt. Okay they have submissions
into their demand side queue for more
this is slightly under date for well
over 200 gawatts of load. Most of this
is speculative. Most of these
submissions are BS. Anybody, not quite
anybody, you can put in a request for a
large load and power without it actually
having financing or a customer or so on.
So most of these things evaporate. But
in any case, the Texas grid operator is
overwhelmed
with these requests for power. And of
course, that just jams up everything.
>> Wait, miss, let me let me ask a quick
question. Are we talking about I have a
data center, I want to connect it to the
grid to get power or I have a new power
source, I want to connect it to to the
grid to deliver power or is it about the
same either way?
>> So this this chart is a generation. So
I've got a new power source and these
two are demand are load
uh interconnection cues
are going up. I mean honest it's much
longer than that. Like today in Urkott
in Texas, the like most advanced
>> progressive
>> least Yeah. most progressive in like a
positive sense like least regulatory
burdened fastest moving grid in the US.
If you put in a request for a hundreds
of megawatts of power to build a data
center today, uh good luck getting that
power before 2031 2032.
>> That's the situation that we have.
>> Yeah. when you did you did a
presentation for my abundance community
on our monthly uh uh meetup and that was
my major takeaway that the issue on
energy for AI isn't you know building on
solar farms it isn't vision or fusion
it's the grid grid's the right
>> so in that case you know and there are
people who are watching who are
investors want to understand this you
know we talk about infrastructure picks
and shovels for AI and we talk about you
know data center construction companies
and all of that who are the companies
that are building the grid and is there
is there sort of work orders and
purchase orders for building out a more
robust grid?
>> It's a really good question. So the grid
the poles and wires the distribution
grid in particular is dominated by
regulatory monopolies, right? to the
local utilities. I I'm not going to
comment on their current pees, whether I
think those stocks are buys or sells,
but the regional monopoly utilities
stand to make a huge amount from this in
the areas where data centers can be
built. There's a separate issue, it's
not in my slides, of more and more uh
voters are pushing back and saying we
want to stop data centers being built.
There's a lot of psychology behind that.
I don't think the the reasons are
necessarily that valid. Uh even in Texas
yesterday, Governor Abbott sent out a
letter pausing. Maybe it was the day
before pausing.
>> Oh, no. Not them, too.
>> He It was actually It wasn't quite a
pause. It's an audit of all data center
requests in Texas.
In Texas, a red state. The most
libertarian state in the country. And
the it's political cover. Abbott knows
that his voters are like there's an
anti-tech sentiment that translates to
AI data centers because they're an
obvious target. So, he wants those data
centers built. There's an election
coming up. He's got to cover his ass for
a bit by making it look like he's
serious about this. Uh but that's the
politics right now in the country.
>> So, so basically we're doomed.
[laughter]
>> I don't think we're
will have space. will always have
sun-synchronous orbit.
>> We we will have sun. [laughter]
>> You know, the AI doomers would say,
"Thank God we're saved. The AI god won't
be built."
But
>> and even if not, they they'd propose
orbital bombardment of the data centers.
There's [laughter] no way of winning.
>> Let me um the grid. Look, I'm going to
show you a lot of like, you know, sci-fi
stuff and awesome stuff, but yeah,
Peter, what you're saying, the grid
itself, the poles and wires are the
limit. And I've talked for years about
the exponentials in solar batteries.
We'll talk about vision and fusion, but
the poles and wires have thus far not
become an exponential technology. And
that's something I would love to solve.
I have not seen a lot of startups.
>> So me, aren't we aren't we moving the
data centers to where the energy is so
you don't need to set up uh you know
>> or disconnecting them from the grid
entirely?
>> Exactly.
>> Let's move. Let's move on and I'll get
from that. This is like a more practical
forecast. You see even like 2028 we'll
we'll build this is probably a little
bit low. The orange is like how much
we'll build. Maybe it'll be 20 30 gawatt
whereas the demand could be much higher.
This is an interesting slice. By the way
I'll tell you every forecaster Morgan
Stanley whoever they all differ somewhat
but this is an interesting slice. The
blue bar is if you just sum up all the
GPU manufacturing
scheduled between now and 2030,
primarily Nvidia, but also AMD, Cerrus,
uh, whoever, versus the expected pace of
US grid buildout, the chips are more
than twice the pace in their power draw.
For folks, the power we can deliver. The
AI demand uh which is chip limited shows
roughly you know 200 to 275
call it 230 gawatt of power demand based
on the chips like you bought the chips
you've installed the chips can you power
the chips there's 230 gawatts of demand
there and US grid buildout is projected
at roughly 100 gawatt
>> and some of you might remember like six
months ago Sachi Nadella CEO of
Microsoft u made this comment look man
warm shells are our limit. We've bought
the chips. We don't have warm shells to
put them in.
>> Right. That is the limit for everyone at
this moment.
>> Yeah. Why why is that discrepancy there?
Because, you know, Eric Schmidt told us
his his number was 100 gawatt or 96
gawatt of additional power by 2030.
Uh the 230 is just based on chip
manufacturing. So either more of the
chips are being kept domestic, which
wouldn't surprise me, or the fabs ramped
up, which would surprise me. But where's
that discrepancy come from?
>> Every single forecaster has a different
number and I think they some of them
base on just announcements by companies
whether they're chip fabs or uh
utilities. Some of them based on their
uh discounted projections of what they
they can actually achieve. Uh also I
will say there's a there's a big miss in
power demand of chips. A lot of people
just say, "How much power can my
Blackwell GPU draw?" Multiply that by
how many you're going to build and
that's the power demand. No, you're
missing like half the power because
you've got to add the draw of the rest
of the IT equipment in the data center
and cooling and so on and that nearly
doubles the total power use.
>> You know, that that would make sense.
those Cerebbrus chips they they run they
just suck down power and they run the
transistors much more efficiently than
the prior generation kind of A100 H100s
from Nvidia. So the transistors are
actually doing a lot more work which is
better fundamentally but yeah of course
that's going to draw more power
constantly and and of course when you
buy those things and deploy them you run
them 24 by7.
>> That's right. You're never going to let
those things rest. So that might be a
discrepancy too.
>> Absolutely. Do do you think me this
creates a forcing function perhaps for
Nvidia or the other fabous vendors or or
the fabs like TSMC to get into the power
generation business right now the power
gen that's that's powering all of these
chips that Satia talks about just
collecting dust in warehouses because he
can't find warm frames for them in data
centers why not why do you think that
there's a forcing function for the
Nvidas of the world to get into powergen
>> well I'd say look whether Nvidia wants
to get into it or not and Nvidia has
made some interesting investments that
I'll talk about in grid flexibility. Uh
the reality is that you know what people
talk about the most now is behind the
meter power gen for data centers. And
what they mean by that is large natural
gas turbines if they can get them. This
is a multiund megawatt like say a 400
megawatt natural gas turbine the kind
you'd use on the grid. These are now
sold out for something like seven years.
uh GE, Hitachi, and so on are building
new assembly lines to try to bring those
online faster, but everyone is saying,
look, if the grid is going to make me
wait years and years and years, I'm just
going to build my own power. Now, this
>> this is more expensive than the grid,
but power is such a small fraction of AI
cost. Maybe you can do it because these
guys are sold out. people are going to
these small turbines. Solar turbines,
nothing to do with solar, but they make
uh this is a 38 megawatt turbine that's
uh on the back of a semi. So 40 of those
make a gigawatt, right? Even these have
backlogs. But now you have companies,
everyone in the world that was in any
way proximate to gas turbines is
pivoting into this space. I'll give you
an example. Bloom Supersonic, very cool
company trying to make uh supersonic
jetliners a thing again. Uh that's a
very hard task with many many billions
of dollars of regulatory costs. They
have pivoted into using their engine
design to make a gas natural gas turbine
for data center power because the demand
for this is so very high.
>> So modular modular energy production,
right? How many of these uh if you think
of them as 18-wheeler truck uh that has
a a large container on the back uh just
pull them in and and get your data
center started until you build out
energy infrastructure and then move them
on.
>> This is how Elon got the Colossus data
centers up uh that Anthropic is now
leasing. Actually, this is what he did.
>> And we've talked a bit about this on on
the pod in the past. We talked about the
boom pivot and we've talked a bit about
Elon standing up his uh fume generating
cogen facilities uh at Colossus etc. We
talked a bit about that but I I just
want to try pressing once more on this
point if if this thesis is true that
this is a primary overhang on Nvidia's
ability to sell more GPUs. Nvidia is
already doing all sorts of financial
engineering to be able to sell more and
more GPUs by through customer financing
all of these other things. Why on earth
if the energy overhang or underhang
depending on your perspective is a major
limiting factor for the ability to
productively monetize GPUs why don't we
see Nvidia doing something on the energy
front?
>> It's a great question. So look for
behind the meter the financial
incentives are so large Nvidia doesn't
have to but they might invest in some of
these companies. Uh on the grid side,
Nvidia has made investments into
increasing grid flexibility to be able
to get more juice out of the current
grid. Emerald AI is one example. They've
made a few investments in this space and
I'll talk about grid flexibility in a
sec here. Uh but the real issue is a
combination of regulatory and the
incentives for utilities. utilities,
monopoly utilities in the US, the bulk
of them are played paid on cost plus. So
they say uh they go to the utility
commission and they say I've got a plan
to meet the demand uh that I see my
customers having. Here's what it costs
for me and I expect a 10% return on
capital for it. And the utility
commission mostly just says okay like
some are better than others. But let's
be honest like the utility has
enormously more horsepower in people
compute salaries etc than the utility
commission. So they like jam through
this plan and they get 10% on top.
>> I see. So, so if I were to try to
synthesize what I think your answer is,
your answer for why Nvidia isn't getting
into bundling power gen with their GPUs
is it's low margin and frictionful like
for the same reason Nvidia tried and
failed and then retreated to launch
their own hyperscaler or Neocloud. It's
just not as high margin as selling GPUs.
You know, Nvidia might still be a
neocloud. We can talk about that
separately. If I was Nvidia, I would be
focused on changing the regulatory
landscape for monopoly utilities. And
I've said this on like some utility
specific podcasts. We should change the
incentives. Utilities instead of just
getting paid uh for uh a percentage over
capex, they should be paid on things
like how fast they can deliver power.
Their executives should get bonuses for
delivering power fast. And if you did
that and they're employees obviously all
the way down. If you did that suddenly
these things would happen faster, right?
>> You get what you incentivize.
Absolutely.
>> Yeah. Look, I invest in startups. How
many startups have I seen that have a
technology to speed up building poles
and wires? I don't know, two or three.
None that I thought were amazing. If
you, by the way, listeners, if you have
one, please send it to me. Why not?
Because there's no incentive for it. But
if you created the incentive, people
would find technical solutions to speed
that process.
>> Is there is there any state? No, not not
Texas, but is there any other state that
is open-minded about that? And
>> Texas Texas is the best. And I will say
despite what I just showed you, Texas
has made policy changes that accelerate
this. And you know people are not
totally asleep with the wheel. FK. So
Texas is interesting. Texas Urkott is
its own fftom. Uh that is not regulated
by the feds at all. Uh FK regulates the
rest of the country's electricity. Uh FK
has sent letters to the six other
largest grids saying basically do
something like what Texas is doing. And
what we're what they're doing is and
maybe I can uh just uh skip to it is
making new regulations that say if you
are an interruptible load, if you are
flexible, if you can uh either find some
alternate way to power yourself or just
turn down your power at moments of peak
demand will get you connected much much
faster. So in uh Texas that's a CLR or a
PCLR an interruptible load. Um and the
reason for that is
we we have as Americans as anyone we
have a very high demands for the
reliability of our grid. Right? 99.9%
uptime is 8 hours of outages per year.
That's unacceptable. Right? It's got to
you got to push to four 9ines to make it
a grid that you think is really good.
But the nature of the grid is the power
demand is not constant. It fluctuates uh
through the course of the day and the
seasons. It peaks uh primarily in the
south in late summer afternoon. So this
is the US grid. The US grid averages
about 500 gawatts of demand uh kind of
throughout the year throughout the day.
it it's much more volatile than that.
But at any given time in like winter
night times, the US grid is down to like
400 gawatts of power being drawn. In uh
summer late afternoon, we're up to like
600 gawatt of power being drawn because
of AC primarily. The fluctuation is
actually much higher than this.
>> Europe doesn't have this problem.
>> I'm [laughter] a joke.
>> It's a different problem. We can talk
about Europe and AC. There's some
amazing tech coming down the pipe on
that. By the way, hopefully a new
investment. Um, that gap
is 200 gawatt, right? 200 gawatt is
about 10 trillion in AI capex. We think
there's about 7 trillion in AI capex in
the next 5 years. Like, this is no joke.
If we just used the poles and wires more
efficiently, we could power up a lot of
stuff because we're not short on
generation. We're not short on power
plants. We are short on capacity and the
poles and wires. Okay. So, what are we
doing there? As I mentioned, like Texas
has, you know, just June enacted this uh
new uh regulatory change that says,
look, if uh you, you know, don't need to
draw power at peak, we'll just hook you
up fast. Instead of five or seven years,
it might be 12 to 18 months. FK has now
told everybody else uh to do that. So,
how do you do that? Uh this is um a
paper by a buddy of mine, Tyler Norris.
uh he's now at Google. He was not when
he wrote this. This came out in January,
February this year. This is the best
electricity related paper of the year in
my mind. And basically what he found was
I call it 200 by 200 or 100 by 100 at
minimum. If you can be flexible 100
hours out of the year, 4 days out of the
year, 1% downtime,
that unlocks 100 gawatt of capacity on
the grid, which is about 5 trillion in
data center capbacks, including the
chips, which gets you through, you know,
the next uh few years. Uh that's one way
to do it is just flexibility. The
startup I mentioned, Emerald AI, uh,
Verun Civerum, uh, funded by Nvidia.
They do this via just software
orchestration, moving jobs to the right
data center, etc., etc., etc. But
there's another way to do this, which is
batteries. Yeah, this is a portfolio
company of mine. I've made three
investments in this same startup, maybe
a fourth one coming up. They do
something really obvious in uh a place
like Dallas Fort Worth between middle of
the night and late afternoon there's
like 10 15 gawatts of flex in the grid
demand. So, if you build out, let's say,
four hours of battery storage at the
site, fill [snorts] it up at midnight,
you don't need to hit it uh during the
peak of the day. And that fits perfectly
with the new Texas regulations. In fact,
they were uh leaders in driving this.
This currently sounds what's obvious to
us, right? But this is an unusual
approach. 12 months from now this will
be a super common approach not just
>> in [clears throat] shifting load right
>> yeah exactly so right now
>> miss but if I if I have a magical
technology that stores insane amounts of
energy very cheaply
>> and I go to even Texas and I say hey
this can completely shift this curve
this is a total game changer can I hook
it up to the grid and start sucking down
power when no one's using it in the
middle of the night would they still say
yeah you can do that in 2030 30.
>> So the new regulations that were just
passed in June gives a fast path to
power for anyone that is an
interruptible load. So so long as the
grid itself, the grid operator is able
to turn you off. It's not them saying
>> definitely we need to make t-shirts that
say I am an interruptible load.
[laughter]
>> Oh my gosh, it makes me want to show an
abundance t-shirt that Peter's team sent
me. But yes, I am an interruptable load.
Uh, don't ask my girlfriend's office.
[laughter]
>> So, look, so Matt, why isn't every data
center uh, you know, deploying these
giant battery packs? It seems like, you
know, if if I had that in my data
center, I would be, you know, super
smooth on the on the load demand for my
community.
>> We passed this regulation in Texas in
June.
>> Okay.
>> Like the second week of June, two months
ago.
>> So, it's brand new.
>> Yeah. So like I invested in these guys
because they drove the regulation and
because they've got 10 gawatt of like
sites that can take advantage of this.
Uh and then after this was passed in
Texas, FK, the federal regular regulator
of electricity sent a letter to the six
largest other grids in the country not
specifying the details but saying do
something like this.
>> Figure this out. So this is going to
become a very common thing to do. And it
[clears throat] it's called a gentic.
Agent Gentic infrastructures.
>> Agent Gentic is the startup. Um but this
in general this is an interruptible load
or timeshifting demand. Again like that
red dashed line. Not all of you some of
you are just listening. The transmission
line capacity and the substation blah
blah blah blah blah transformers. That's
the limit. It's not the gas generators
or the solar or wind. It's the
transmission line. So, if you can use
batteries to fill up your data center,
your data center batteries at night when
the transmission line is unused and then
not need to draw on the transmission
during the day, that is we've always
known that was a good idea. We do it
with with EVs and so on. Um, and this is
a a very big deal. [clears throat]
>> Amazing. Would you would you say me this
is it it's fair to characterize this as
the energy or the grid equivalent of uh
preemptive multitasking or re-entrant
multitasking in computing? Basically
allowing processes to say they can be
paused and their compute load can be
timeshifted.
>> Yeah, I think that's one way to look at
it. I think that's a great analogy,
Alex. It's also like cache prefill, you
know, like yes, batteries are a cache
for electrons instead of data.
So we're we're making our grid cachable.
>> That's right. By the way,
>> go ahead.
>> How what you know that big gap of the
200 gawatts, how much of that do you
think we can make a dent in by taking
[snorts] this approach?
>> I think approaches like this and
approaches like electric vehicles also,
right? The the bulk of the batteries in
the US are actually in EVs. So, another
company of mine, Weave Grid, uh I
shouldn't say of mine, like I'm blessed
to be an investor in them because
they're smarter than I am. Uh they're
they have long for utilities managed
electric vehicle charging on the grid to
reduce stress on the last mile, on the
last block even, right? The limit on EV
charging for the grid is actually the
transformer on your block because
Tesla's cluster. If one person gets a
Tesla, their neighbor like doubles in
odds of getting a Tesla, right? So they
already have software to like time slice
and even out the charging of the
vehicles. So companies like that in
particular weave grid are using that
technology to make the rest other loads
on the grid more responsive and shaped
in a way to allow uh AI data centers to
play well. In fact, every EV charging
company I know has pivoted to trying to
use their tech or their current capacity
to enable data centers. And I think
that's 100 gawatts. I think that's if
we're smart about it, that's the next
five years of AI data center growth.
>> Amazing. All right, what's next?
>> All right, let's talk uh like uh more
interesting stuff. We all love solar. Uh
let me tell you uh we are we're entering
the phase where
solarp powered AI data centers become
viable. Uh many people have seen a chart
like this I've shown in 75 1975 uh one
watt of solar panels cost 100 bucks. Uh
now it's 8 cents from China for a panel
that's smaller has a longer lifetime is
more durable etc. And so uh that more
than 1000x price decline does that get
us to the point where we can power data
centers with it? Well data centers
because the chips are so expensive it
never makes economic sense to only run
them when the sun shines. So you have to
storage as well. Battery prices have
dropped by a factor of 14 since 2010. We
have new technologies like lithium ion
has been dominant. Sodium is much more
common on planet Earth than lithium. So
new technologies like sodium ion
batteries could drop the cost of
batteries by a factor of 10. And even
now we already have the very first solar
plus battery load power plants and
they're affordable. So we have them in
the UAE outside of Dubai. We have them
in Chile. And a nice thing about this is
honestly uh you know natural gas
turbines are sold out for years. You can
the fastest energy project you can build
is a solar and battery project. You can
get that done in 12 months.
>> So we in the United Arab Emirates this
is a 1 gawatt 247 solar and battery
project. What that means is they
guarantee that the minimum power output
at any time is a g gawatt. to do that.
It's actually 5 gawatts of solar and 19
gatt hours of batteries. And the cost is
like is six bucks a watt capex. That
won't mean a lot to a lot of people. But
let's just say the last nuclear power
plant built in the US cost $15 a watt.
Uh the cheapest ones on planet Earth are
Chinese. Uh being built in China, those
are $4 a watt.
>> So recently competitive.
>> It is is recently competitive. So, so
Nez, you and I texted about this, right?
On the last earnings call at Tesla, I
think it was at Tesla, uh, Elon said he
wanted to build out 100 gawatts of solar
capacity. Did you check into that?
>> Yeah. I mean, [snorts] I think, look,
it's a long-term vision. It's not next
year, but Elon's overall vision is let's
put all the compute in space. There's no
land constraints. There's no permitting
uh uh issues there. People won't
complain about water use there. and he
wants to build a terowatt of AI. Uh, and
if you're going to build a terowatt of
AI, you've got, you know, two or three
options really. The world's deserts
powered by solar and batteries. Uh,
getting fision or fusion to work. Uh,
ocean power like panas that I'll show or
space.
>> So, he's talking about about Tesla
building out solar, terrestrial solar,
right? Competing competing with China.
>> Yeah. He wants to build out the
manufacturing for it, but I think his
real motivation is not selling it to the
onland market in the US. I think his
real motivation is to build that uh
manufacturing capacity uh for
space-based solar.
>> If you look at what is we need a pedoph
just pull on that Peter's question me
just a bit. If if we take the thousandx
reduction per kilowatt or megawatt o
over the past few decades and
extrapolate it, have you gone through
the thought experiment of what would
solar need to look like in order to
achieve another thousandx price per watt
reduction?
>> Yes. So this is a very good question and
it's it's an important um clarification
of how the cost reductions work. So our
best model I'm not that smart, right?
Like I I'm one of the top five
forecasters of solar costs in the world.
And it's not because I'm that smart.
It's because I came out of tech and I
came from a Moore's law world and came
into energy and just applied Moore's law
to it. But when you actually look at the
details, it's not a reduction in time.
It's a reduction with cumulative scale.
It is Wright's law. It's the learning
rate. So every cumulative doubling of
solar scale reduces costs by let us say
30%. it you know it fluctuates yeartoear
it's the real world and so on so look if
we ignore the possibility that we need
terowatts of AI compute and we just look
at the world as it is uh solar is now 8%
of global electricity and let's say we
think solar can get to a third or 2/3 uh
and maybe electricity demand goes up by
a factor of two you've got four five six
doublings left that means the cost of
solar might drop by a factor of four
maybe even by a factor of eight but not
by a factor of a thousand. But if you
start talking about uh you know building
Dyson spheres then we have a long way to
go to keep reducing those costs.
>> I heard what I wanted to hear.
[laughter]
>> You heard Dyson spheres
>> pandering pandering.
[laughter]
>> Bingo. Wait, can I
drill in on that too?
>> I've got a couple of questions.
Yeah, Romez, how many of these
installations are there being built
around the [snorts] world right now?
Like this exact style of monster scale
uh solar at scale.
>> We're just Oh, like gigawatt scale, you
know, a handful uh largely in China, the
Middle East, uh some in Latam. Uh we
have, you know, a maybe more than a
handful, maybe a dozen at this scale.
Most solar plants today, you know,
they're typically somewhere between 50
megawws and a few hundred megawws. a
gigawatt plant. The the challenge and
the reason the biggest reason this is
not yet an option for the US because we
could pull off something like this in
the southwest and it would actually it
would be cheap. It would be more
expensive than it is in the Emirates
because our labor costs are higher, but
it would be fast. You could have it done
in a year with even a natural gas
turbine that you want to order from G.
You can't do that. But putting together
the land parcels is actually the pain
for this
>> in the US.
>> Me are these are these solar panels
coming from China?
>> Probably. I mean 85% do. So presumably
and of course we double the price of
Chinese solar panels in the US. So we
hurt ourselves by keeping them out.
>> Sorry.
>> Yeah. So if this is the fastest path to
energy at scale, why aren't there people
just going or the US government just
going, "Yeah, let's let's use eminent
domain, grab whatever chunks of land we
need to and [snorts] build this stuff
because we could be done in a year."
>> You don't need eminent domain. The
federal government is the number one
land owner west of the Mississippi. And
those federal lands are concentrated in
places like Nevada, Arizona, places that
have enormous solar resources. Uh, but
it's not something that interests the
current administration, I would say. But
yeah, if I was thinking about it, I'd be
thinking about how do we open up lands
that are not not amazing uh nature
resources uh to build solar powered data
centers. And I think we get them.
Sunshine seems better than drilling on
federal land.
>> Absolutely. And I I'll say this also
like regulations are the problem in lots
of place. I was in Mexico recently. I
was in Chihuahua and uh you know trying
to convince the government of Chihuahua,
a state of Mexico uh to build a lot of
solar powered AI data centers. But in
Chihuahua, it is actually illegal to
have a private power generation, a
behind the meter power above, I think it
was 500 kilowatts, right? Half a
megawatt. So you just use the law can't
do it. And then secondly, the AI labs
and the hyperscalers are extremely
vigilant about data protections. They
don't want their user data leaked or
seized and they especially don't want
their model weights excfiltrated. So
they're they're pretty careful about the
countries they go into. So my advice to
Mexico was like look you know change the
laws to make it possible to build this
sort of thing and to pro provide
ironclad guarantees of the protection
and say you know intellectual property
protection of this data and you've got
an enormous business right more open
land lower population density and better
sun than the US.
>> This episode is brought to you by Blitzy
autonomous software development with
infinite code context. Blitzy uses
thousands of specialized AI agents that
think for hours to understand enterprise
scale code bases with millions of lines
of code. Engineers start every
development sprint with the Blitzy
platform, bringing in their development
requirements. The Blitzy platform
provides a plan, then generates and
pre-ompiles code for each task. Blitzy
delivers 80% or more of the development
work autonomously while providing a
guide for the final 20% of human
development work required to complete
the sprint. Enterprises are achieving a
5x engineering velocity increase when
[music] incorporating Blitzy as their
preIDE development tool, pairing it with
their coding co-pilot of choice to bring
an AI native SDLC into their org. Ready
to 5x your engineering velocity? Visit
blitzy.com to schedule a demo and start
building with Blitzy today.
I was going to push back on on well
first thing first the uh the GPUs can't
sit idle no matter what because they're
so expensive and yeah but when you look
at the underlying economics about 5% of
the cost of the data center maybe up to
10% is the power but the GPU itself is
80% markup from Nvidia on top of 2x
markup from TSMC with another 2x markup
at the model provider level so it's
actually 20x overpriced relative to the
cost of turning sand into a chip which
is actually coming down too with
efficiency and scale and so at the where
Elon thinks at the fundamental level uh
it's actually not a given that the GPU
is super expensive relative to the power
once he gets the terapab up and running
and the end to end sand in one side chip
out the other is fully automated so that
would completely flip all the math in
this if he if he gets to that
destination I think those are awesome
comments, Dave, and I think it's right
that GPUs are are overpriced, or at
least there's a lot of margin going in
there. Uh, Nvidia, people don't think of
them as a network effect company, but
CUDA, the programming layer to write to
AI is like their moat, right? It's not
like their chips are good,
>> their chips are fine. AMD's chips are as
good. Their interconnection between
chips is great, and that does matter,
but people like uh Huawei is kind of
getting there, honestly. Uh but CUDA has
been the moat and I think the CUDA moat
is broken this year and next year. One
of my portfolio companies, Lamorian, I
met them at Abundance 360 is working on
that. But also now that you can tell AI
take my uh AI code and recompile it to
run really fast on this AMD chip or the
Cabus chip. I think Nvidia's lead is
>> so glad you brought that up. This is
such an important topic because this $5
trillion of US market cap that's that's
hanging in the balance of this
conversation. It's such an important and
such a fragile thing, you know. So, CUDA
is the moat for sure. No doubt. All the
AI researchers are too lazy to write
custom kernels. Suddenly, Fable 5 comes
along. I've had great luck running
custom kernels myself just in the last
couple weeks using Fable 5. So, so I
think your prediction is is probably
right. I don't see why it wouldn't be
right. Uh I think Nvidia would say we
have all kinds of other network effects
and we have massive interconnect. Now
the interconnect is incredibly important
for training.
>> Yeah.
>> But 90 95% of the load now is moving to
inference
>> where you don't really need the
interconnect.
>> I think the internet still is very
helpful for inference. you know, if
you're going to run a model like uh
Kimmy K3 or DeepSeek, not necessarily
flash, but the next DeepSseek V4, you're
you're simultaneously running it on a
rack, right? You're running it on 10 to
20 uh GPUs at a time. So, the
interconnect does matter somewhat even
for inference. But you're right that it
matters even more, tremendously more for
training. Can I Dave's point is is just
that in at inference time interconnect
locally matters to the extent you need
local coherence but you no longer need
global coherence at the level of an
entire supercluster. It's just like a
single rack of coherence.
>> Yeah, that's correct.
>> Coming back to energy and to summarize
this, there's plenty of room for energy
growth. We have the abundance thesis on
energy writ large with solar, right? And
and one of the points that Elon's made
before is at the end of the day, it's
all about solar. every do you believe
that do you believe that thesis that
solar in the long term is going to
dominate beyond everything else?
>> It's complicated and and I think we
underestimate the importance of
geography. So the the reality is look
from a regulatory standpoint we're not
building transmission. We are no place
of China is building enough capacity to
move electrons from place to place. Same
thing as what I just showed with poles
and wires. And so the problem for solar
is uh not cost and it's not nighttime
because batteries are plunging in cost
and are going to drop another 10x
ultimately. Uh it is winter. So in
London for instance, [clears throat]
you get 16th or 17th as much insulation
in January as you do in June or July. So
you're going to build out your solar
plant by a factor of six or seven?
>> No.
uh or do you have do we have a battery
technology that can store months of
power? Just a couple interesting ideas
out there, but like think about, you
know, the unit cost electricity goes to
a battery. It basically battery capex
amortized by how many times it gets
used. So if you got a battery that
cycles daily, it's like battery cost,
you know, capex divided by 365 or uh,
you know, 3,650 if it's 10 years, let's
say. If the battery gets used like twice
to shift load between seasons, it's
battery capex divided by that. So there
are there's numerous startups, there's
some crazy ideas, sand, compressed air,
power to natural gas, yada yada yada.
But right now like it's clear to me that
economically shifting battery shifting
energy through the day night cycle we're
not totally there yet but it is like the
curves are are just heading that way. uh
but dealing with winter especially also
we have not yet electrified heat and if
you look at you know the UK as an
example and in case in Northern Europe
uh if you go from burning natural gas
for building heat to using heat pumps
electricity demand uh like doubles in
winter. So we have this big big big
winter problem that I think a lot of
people are not reckoning with. And so I
do believe, you know, nuclear is super
useful as is, you know, efforts to get
uh seasonal storage, as are all of our
efforts on fusion, as is advanced
geothermal. Um be especially for those
places that are further from the equator
and have either long winters or long
rainy seasons.
>> Location, location, location.
>> Yeah. All right. So this is this last
slide is saying that that solar battery
data center is going to get cheaper and
cheaper. And so yes, one of you asked
why don't we move compute to where the
energy is and I fully believe that right
in other energy loads you can't move the
population of New York City to a place
that's sunny year round not quickly
>> almost is Florida [laughter]
>> okay it's Miami uh during co and uh
mostly for crypto folks uh but you can
uh the new load we haven't built which
is AI why don't we site it where the
energy is right so that's that's that's
one viewpoint. All right. Um, next, uh,
Peter, you wanted me to talk about
vision and fusion and both are super
exciting.
>> Absolutely. Yeah. I mean, we hear a lot
about it. We talk about it. We we speak
about the hyperscalers turning on, uh,
you know, defunct fision plants,
investing in fusion companies.
>> U, you know, it's interesting. A quick
stat. Uh 71% of Americans are against
data centers, which is a higher
percentage than are against a nuclear
plant in their backyard, which I find
amazing.
>> That's just insane. I'd rent my backyard
out to both. It's not big enough quiet,
but uh you know, [laughter]
we'll we'll make some room. Um
>> maybe just a quick question before the
the segue. I just want to pull a little
bit on the historic rhyme between the
Middle East being a major source of oil
but now also being a major source of
solar power. If the the thought
experiment I've done, I'd be curious to
get your thoughts, is the reason the
Middle East has so much oil is my
understanding is like hundreds of
millions of years ago, there used to be
a a warm ocean with lots of plankton and
other small creatures that ultimately
resulted in the oil. And now it's it's
largely desert, but still it's pretty
warm. Any thoughts on the the historic
rhyme between why somehow Middle East is
on the one hand supplier of all this oil
power [snorts] for data centers and now
potentially solar power.
>> Well, I think the Middle East has
amazing solar resources, but it's not as
lumpy as their uh fossil fuel resources
and especially their oil resources. Um
if you look around the globe, you have
Australia. I mean, if I was thinking,
actually, I just said Mexico. If I was
thinking about let's do a lot of solar
and batterypowered data centers for AI,
I would be really pushing in Australia.
>> Yeah. You've got a friendly government,
you've got enormous amounts of space,
you've got the some of the world's best
uh solar resources. Uh Chile and Mexico,
not amazing oil producers. Mexico was
once, they're not anymore. uh but solar
resources that are you know equivalent
to the Middle East. Uh so if you look
around the world it's interesting uh we
obviously we all know intuitively you
know some places are much sunnier than
others but in the places that people
live the actual like solar energy that
falls varies by at most a factor of two
between the least sunny and most sunny
places which is kind of crazy. Yeah. the
seasonal effect is bigger, right? And as
you get further from the equator, the
seasonal effect uh gets bigger. I live
in Seattle, I know this. [laughter]
Whereas the oil density underground is
much much much higher dispersion, much
higher concentration in a few spots. So
overall, like when I when I'm always
counseling them on find a way to export
energy. You're not going to build poles
and wires to move electricity from Saudi
Arabia to the US. But, you know, he used
to say like steel like Iceland uh is
makes a lot of aluminum. They have no
bulkite ore, but they have cheap
geothermal. Uh I know I've got a company
I've been talking to right now that's
using Icelandic geothermal to make uh uh
sustainable aviation fuels like e-
fuels, power to fuels uh because they
can export that, right? So if I was in
Saudi, I used to say like make
industrial uh uses of electricity, but
now I just say like make data, make
intelligence,
>> but you've got to change the laws such
that an open AI, an anthropic, a Grock,
whoever, a Google
>> is comfortable citing their crown jewels
in your country. Just by way of a
reference number for the audience, you
know, when I last looked at it uh on the
energy abundance thesis, you know, we
have 8,000 times more energy than hits
the surface of the earth and we consume
as a species in a year, right? So,
there's plenty of energy out there. It's
just not in usable form. And the whole
conversation here is how do we take that
energy that's latent and make it usable,
right? And that's the role of
technology.
>> That's right. The other the other
commentary is that the fossil fuel are
just an old battery that we've been
using up, right? Uh and and we've used
up about 25% or 30% of that battery.
>> No one knows. But I mean, you know, the
cure for high prices is high prices. So
if we ever started to run low, there'd
be more incentive to explore and find
stuff. Y
>> I have a question for you, Romez, on the
on the oil market. real quick. I
remember you commenting once [snorts]
that the 2013 oil price, oil crisis, oil
crash
>> was because of a 2% over supply in the
market. Like it's a really tightly won
market.
>> Is that still the case or with all the
Middle East conflict and everything
else, we're now in tension, it's going
to stay that way?
>> Oh my gosh. I mean, there's a lot to say
about that. Look, like two interesting
things. Yeah, there's two interesting
things about the the Iran war and its
impact on oil prices and why it's been
relatively muted. Uh number one, China
did us all a solid. China built the
world's largest uh oil strategic
reserve, right? And they were willing to
drain it during this period. So, China
has, you know, more than the rest of the
world's uh strategic reserves combined
has helped keep oil prices low. But two,
the ratio of global GDP to global
spending on oil has roughly tripled or
quadrupled since the oil crisis of the
70s. So, there are critical things that
are highly dependent upon oil, you know,
aviation, shipping, trucking, and so on.
But overall the world has moved to more
of a services economy and that has
created you know sort of more uh demand
elasticity. It has allowed the world to
deal with a shortfall in oil in a way
that we couldn't in the 70s when our
economy is just more physical.
>> Maybe you haven't seen oil spike to 200
bucks and
>> I just like to pull in the the
geopolitical angle here. There there's a
a theory in certain circles that uh an
ulterior motive for the Venezuelan
operation and then uh the war with Iran
was actually to cut off China's uh in
event of a Chinese invasion of Taiwan uh
open PN TSMC closed PN that China would
require backup oil supplies because they
would get embargoed by the Western block
and their go-to sources for backup oil
in such an invasion would be would look
like Venezuela, Iran, maybe Cuba. And so
so the the the full sort of theory here
is the the recent military adventures
that we've seen, Venezuela, Iran are
actually at some level a play to deter
China from invading Taiwan to gain
access to the TM TSMC fabs and basically
the future light code of AI. Any
thoughts on that?
>> There's insight there, but I don't agree
with it as stated. And the reason for
that is uh China bought oil from Iran
during the this this war. The US still
sells oil to China. Uh it just wasn't
that planned out. Um the actual DoD war
plans uh in a situation like that are to
use the US submarine fleet to sink
tankers that are getting heading to
China. That's the actual, you know,
proposal of what to do. Who knows if
that's a good idea. I I'm not going to
get into that right now. Oil is mostly
funible. So, the fact that China buys
oil from Iran, us bombing Iran, uh or
even if we successfully close the
straight doesn't really hurt China that
much because they can buy cargos from
somewhere else, they were getting a
discount from Iran because it was
embargoed oil and that they were willing
to buy. So, they have to pay, you know,
a few bucks more per barrel. It's not
that big a deal to them. In wartime,
it's a kinetic uh sanction. It's a
kinetic embargo. Uh which is a different
sort. And yeah, the the sim I think this
is all totally unclassified. The
simulations of wars like that are US
submarines, you know, torpedo tankers
that are heading to China.
>> Onwards to the horizon of fision and
fusion.
>> Okay. Uh let's talk about the atom and
the power thereof going back to the 50s
or you know a retro future. Uh uh this
is a complicated slide uh for those of
you who are uh just listening. Basically
there's you know two approaches to
nuclear fision which is what we've been
doing since the 60s. The traditional one
is big reactors and the simplest thing
you can do to boost nuclear production
worldwide is a stop shutting down
nuclear plants. Germany should not have
shut down. It's uh two nuclear plants
have like a end of life plant. We can
usually extend them. In some cases, we
can actually upgrade them to produce
more power. Uh three, there are some
plants that have been shut down like 3M
island that we can actually restart
safely. But that gets you, you know, a
few gigawatts, right? If we really want
a nuclear renaissance, the the core
issue with nuclear fision today is that
outside of China and perhaps South
Korea, it is ruinously expensive. And
why is it ruinously expensive? It's
because we don't do a lot of it.
Anything that you do infrequently is
expensive,
right? You don't get good at the things
you do occasionally. the things that are
cheap are the things that you do
repeatedly again and again and again. So
there are two paths happening uh to
bolster nuclear in the US. And I'm a
critic of this administration on on many
fronts and on some energy fronts, but
I'd say this administration has the best
nuclear policies of any in recent
history. Still missing some things, I
think, but the best that we've seen. Uh
so the left side of this is large
reactors. We have this thing called the
AP-1000. It's sort of a it's the
Westinghouse reactor. It's sort of a
workhouse uh reactor. We've built a
couple of them in the west, let's say
four. Uh China took a variant, took this
design, made their own variant that had
a local supply chain, and they've built
more than a dozen. And they built them
at higher power than this, 1.4 gawatt
instead of 1 gawatt. So, one plan is
we're going to produce uh a process to
get more of these built. The
administration is talking about has
created structures for loan guarantees,
for financing and so on because if you
stamp out a lot of these, the cost
should come down. Right now,
>> what plant is the most stamped out so
far? [snorts]
>> Uh,
lightwater reactors like those used in
France. So, France uh is the poster
child. Uh, the US has generates the most
nuclear electricity of any country on
earth. Actually, it's it's not really
known. Uh, China is building the most
right now. France gets the highest
fraction of it electricity from nuclear
and they basically with slight caveats
basically took the same design and
stamped it out again and again and
again.
>> How many of France have like 60 nuclear
power plants now?
>> Something on that order. Yep. But even
France
>> something like something 80% of their
electricity is nuclear. It's crazy.
>> And they exported to the rest of the
Euro zone as well. efficient was
basically born in France. Thank you,
Curies.
>> Yeah, but even France is strug
struggling, right? There's something
called the European pressurized reactor
which is mostly a French design and that
thing is kind of a a disaster right now.
It's a boondoggle running over going
slow. Again, like if you take one design
and you do a lot of it, it gets cheap.
But usually, and this is critical for
the sector as an investor, the first one
usually runs over price over time uh and
you know has problems you didn't
anticipate. So if you want a thriving
nuclear industry, you just have to know
that the first one you build of a new
model is probably going to have
problems. But after you've built three,
four, five, maybe more, you sort out
those problems. You build experience in
the crews. You build experience in the
engineers. You sort out design issues.
You build a supply chain to provide the
parts that you need. So one plan is
we're going to take the large reactors
that we have built a couple times. And
now we have the US government has
created financing sort of a backs stop
loan guarantees for about eight of
these. Um another startup the nuclear
company I invested in one of the
founders previous companies. uh they
have a plan to basically build fleets of
these because that's how you have to
finance it. You can't finance one
because you know you're going to miss
your targets. But if you can finance a
bunch at a time amortize the cost
>> you know in China like after they got to
like 6 7 8 like the costs had really
come down and stabilized.
>> So those who are fearful about nuclear
and it's still you know probably
[snorts] a good percentage they they
think about three-mile island in
Fukushima. We're talking about early
generation plants right? Are those gen
Gen 1 or gen two plants?
>> Something like that. And these are uh
gen 3 or gen 3 plus or gen 4 plants. And
one of the most important things to
understand about them is basically all
of these are passive safe. What that
means is um you can knock out the power
to them and they won't have a meltdown.
Fukushima happened because you circulate
water around the nuclear core to take
the heat away from it and then use it to
turn a steam turbine. That pump for that
was powered by grid electricity. So the
tsunami that hit Fukushima knocked out
the power lines and so the pumps stopped
working even though there's power right
next to them for the nuclear reactor.
Right. New nuclear fision designs are
passive safe.
>> Would you call them fail failsafe
plants? Nothing is totally failsafe, but
they're designed to take a 747 crashing
into them and the power going out from
the grid and keep operating without any
meltdown.
>> I [clears throat] I'm curious, just
pulling on that, MZ, what happened in
the 1970s? I assume you've seen the
television show, we we talk about it
sometimes on the pod for all mankind.
It's sort of an alternative historic
reality where we get vision, it never
gets abandoned. What happened in the
70s? Did did we just waste the past 50
years not building enough nuclear energy
vision in particular finding ourselves
in a sub-optimal future?
>> I don't think so exactly. I think we
could have done better but people are
somewhat riskaverse. Uh radiation we
learned you know in the 60s that
radiation causes cancer. The radiation
released from a well operating nuclear
plant is really minimal. it's unlikely
to cause uh cancer. But so we we did
increase the regulatory estate. We did
increase the burden of proving that
things were safe and that had some cost
and then uh things just fizzled out and
and you know we talk a lot about um
flywheels and and positive feedback
loops. We had a negative feedback loop
once and this is the same thing
Francisine once the industry is no
longer building. you lose the expertise,
you lose the supply chain that makes the
parts that you need, you lose the
manufacturing facilities, uh, and
everything gets more expensive. So, if
you're not constantly scaling, you are
going to backslide basically.
>> [clears throat]
>> So those were large reactors and you
have on this slide here the small
modular reactors because
>> the right side and this is the area that
investors are super stoked about uh that
I was stoked about 15 years ago got less
stoked about and now I'm kind of
becoming maybe hopeful again is what we
call small modular reactors. So we talk
about a lot I talk a lot about learning
rates, right? Which is how fast does
something get cheap. And every
technology if you build more of it gets
cheap at some rate as the scale
increases. But the things that get
cheapest the fastest are those that are
built in factories in high volume and
have the smallest number of moving
parts. So the idea of SMRs is to build
as much of this in modular, repeatable,
factorybuilt
uh situations as possible and do as
little stick building, as little
assembly or construction. Construction
is a dirty word, right? Construction
does not get cheaper. Manufacturing gets
cheaper. So move as much of this as we
can to a manufacturing process. uh at
the limit it's a factory that spits out
nuclear reactors that you just you know
barge or semi-truck to location. Uh some
of these are not that many of these are
uh the parts are made in a factory in a
standardized way that you assemble like
Legos on site. This is an incredibly uh
sexy space uh for investors right now.
Uh yesterday we found out that Valar
Atomics uh raised a billion dollars at a
$6 billion valuation for ASMR startup
that that doesn't have a working
reactor. Uh you other companies Alo is
probably my favorite company in the
space, but there's a ton of companies.
>> My friend's company at X Energy uh went
public recently.
>> Xenergy is an amazing company actually.
I I really like their design. Uh so
that's the radiant is one on here that
that's on a the very very small scale.
There's a a line between uh SMR and
micro reactor. So can you make it small
enough to fit in a shipping container?
Uh so the military for instance you got
radiant is on this slide. uh the US
military for military bases would like
shipping container or half shipping
container sized reactors to power bases
in the US but maybe in forward deployed
locations as well so they don't have to
move fuel. So there's a lot happening in
this space.
>> So Natrium I see on the chart here is
you know a third of a gigawatt
>> compared to the AP-1000 which is roughly
a gigawatt. when you say, you know, if
if Natrium goes into mass production,
mass production being tens, you know, 50
units, I mean, the relative price of
buying three of those Natrium units
versus an AP1 1000. What's that? You
know, is there economies to bigger
plants or is it you stack them together?
>> Yeah, there are economies, bigger
plants. Bigger plants use uh less steel
and less cement per, you know, unit of
power output. So there are economies to
bigger plants and that's how we used to
think in the 50s and 60s primarily. Uh
but there's learning that happens from
building more plants and doing more of
it in a factory. So personally my guess
is like the BWRx 300 Natrium are in a
awkward middle uh because they're not
really factory built. They build a bunch
of components in the factory to do field
assembly and so I worry about them but
they might end up being the ideal
optimal solution. At the other end of
the spectrum you got like gradient here.
Their reactor is 10 megawws. So it's
1/100th the size of an AP 1000. They put
them together in in clusters of five.
That's a pod for 50 megawws.
uh they have lower efficiency of using
steel and cement but uh they can build
it entirely inside of a factory.
>> Which is the first one of these we're
you know these are not online yet these
are all theoretical which is the first
one coming online you think?
>> Yeah. So um the optimistic projections
from these companies are 2030 to the
early 2030s. Uh and uh that's for the
small ones. The next AP-1000 is probably
a few years later than that. Uh these
projections will probably be missed. I
don't expect anyone to actually have a
commercial small modular reactor in 2030
2031, but maybe not. Like the the size
of slip is probably smaller for a small
reactor. And like everything else we've
been saying, the first units here are
not going to be cheap. the first years
are going to be expensive. So the key is
to build an order book from a customer
that believes that by ordering enough
they're going to drive down the price.
Uh or to build a you know a multi-c
customer order book where you've built
some mechanism for cost and risk sharing
between these AI data centers and we
talk about is nuclear the solution for
AI data centers. Maybe there's other
ways to power AI. Uh but AI data centers
might be uh the best thing that's ever
happened to the nuclear industry.
>> I'm curious me if we just take this
argument in extremists, where are the
nano reactors? Why don't we see 100
kilowatt nano pico reactors that can be
colllocated with every GPU? Do you think
there's an opportunity in the space
there?
>> I think it's really hard. I think you
you do hit some economies of scale
issues as you get down to the bottom and
you do you have a certain size for
criticality but you have you know on
this chart at the bottom here you have
you know with companies like gradient
you have like five megawatt uh size
reactors and that's you know power
a neighborhood or power or a few of them
powering a military base that sort of
scale
>> and do you also
>> it's just expensive right
>> well I mean there are many ways one
could imagine doing and another would be
like gamma voltaics or beta voltaics
like you put the radionuclides directly
in the silicon and then you you pocket
the energy from uh radioactive decay. Do
you think there's any hope for for those
who want to embed radionuclides directly
in the GPU silicon?
>> I mean that that's what we talked about
as you know uh radiothermal or nuclear
thermal and that's different than than a
fision reactor. We use that on
satellites or the deep space probes. We
use do radiothermal. Absolutely.
>> RTGs. Yeah.
>> Um Yeah. I don't expect to see RTGs
become popular on Earth. When you look
at the cost of those, they're actually
really high, but they can meet, you
know, mission needs for something that
keeps on putting out power for decades
without needing to be refueled. But
their power output per unit mass is not
all that high. Aren't those just
constantly spewing radiation though?
>> That that is the idea. [laughter]
>> I mean, but in a bad way, too.
>> Like, okay.
>> Yeah. Ouch.
>> I'll let you figure that one out.
>> So, so let me just
>> It's really interesting how you've got
this foot race between, you know, if you
said early 2030s for all these nuclear
projects, but Elon is racing into space
concurrent with that and solar, you
said, is coming down 30% every time we
double
>> the production. So, all those things are
in a foot race
>> and fusion's got the same time frame,
right? We're no longer 50 years in
waiting. We're 5 years in waiting.
Welcome to the health section of
Moonshots brought to you by Fountain
Life. You know, my mission is to help
you use the latest technologies,
including AI, to not just do your work
at home, teach your kids, but to help
you live a long and healthy life. I'm
here today with an extraordinary
physician, the chief medical officer of
Fountain Life, Dr. Don Mucalem. Dawn,
let's talk about cancer. Uh, you know, I
know from the member database that we've
have at Fountain are members who come in
who think they're healthy. It turns out
3.3% of them have a cancer in their body
they don't know about.
>> That's right. You know, the majority of
cancers that we screen for, those aren't
the ones that are necessarily taking the
lives when found at a late stage. We
know that when cancer is found early,
the chances for cure are much higher. We
know it's much easier to treat a cancer
when found early versus when found late.
What we're finding in our members is
over 3.3% were found to have these
cancers that were otherwise wouldn't
have been found or detected.
>> Yeah. You know, it's interesting.
People, you don't feel the cancer until
stage three or stage four. And and if
you don't know what's going on inside
your body, it's like driving your car
with your eyes closed and you can know.
And so when members come through found,
how do they detect cancers?
>> So we're doing full body MRI and we also
do early cancer detection screening.
This is very very important. These are
not typical tools used in the
conventional care setting when it comes
to prevention. This is a hard thing
because currently these are not studies
that insurance would yet be covering.
But the goal is to collect these
numbers, do the research, and work hard
to democratize wellness.
>> Yeah. So, at the end of the day, you can
know what's going on inside your body.
It's your obligation to know. So, check
out Fountain Life. You can go to
fountainlife.com/pater
to get access to the latest technology
to help you detect cancer at the very
beginning at stage one when it is
curable before it gets to stage three or
stage four in your world of hurt. Let's
uh let's hit to to fusion. This this lie
just says stuff I've already said. The
main thing I want to tell you is like
hyperscaler saying oh we're like using
SMRs for our data center. It's still
kind of a fiction. It's I mean it's it's
outside the five-year window that we
really can that is investable that we
really have like really good optics on
but the the pull from data centers is
giving a massive uh you know tailwind to
every nuclear company uh in especially
this SMR startups but also even
Westinghouse with their with their big
reactors. Let's talk fusion.
>> All right. The joke was always that uh
that fusion is 50 years in the future
and always will be. That's just no
longer true. Um
we now have well over 50 fusion
startups.
Uh we had
>> venturebacked fusion companies. I mean
that's like science fiction in its own
right.
>> That's right. Absolutely.
Uh some of these ironically came because
of budget cuts in academia. If you look
at Commonwealth Fusion, which is
considered sort of the safe bet of
fusion, if you will, if there is such a
thing, uh that that team at Harvard uh
you know, their grants uh were
struggling and so they said, "Why don't
we form a company you guys?" And so they
did and they're now uh the front runner.
They have a a uh how can I say this? I
don't want to call any fusion reactor a
conservative design, but they have like
[laughter] the most conservative design
in this sci-fi field of fusion.
>> There's a striking resemblance. Yeah. A
friend of mine from uh college and grad
school as always is on their board. You
you could call it like a privatization
of MIT's entire nuclear engineering
department.
>> Yeah, indeed. Indeed. And and not just
that of Eater. You know, we have we've
had publicly funded fusion projects. N
in the US uses big lasers national
facility. It's really a weapons facility
is what it is and EER in France the
international and European project that
was at Tokamac uh that is the you know
the the big doughut style uh and's plan
was to build you know a reactor that was
at least 5 gawatt and would cost at
least $40 billion
right and so what you have with CFS is a
company has found a way to scale that
down. So here here's how I think about
the three families of Fusion. This is a
massive oversimplification. My Fusion
startup founder friends are going to
yell at me for not including their
particular designs, but you know there's
three big ones. Tokamax are the donuts
that use big magnets to guide a plasma
around and make that plasma slam into
itself and capture the energy. That's
what Eater is. That's where we have the
most scientific data from past
experiments about fusion. And the
leading company in this space,
Commonwealth Fusion, CFS, basically just
has a technology uh that takes the
enormous superconducting magnets that we
were going to use in this European
project and shrinks them down
dramatically. We have a thin film
material that you can wind around and
wrap around that makes the magnet
dramatically smaller. And because it's a
superconducting magnet, you got to cool
it tremendously. And now that it's much
smaller, you need a lot less cooling uh
energy, there's a lot lower capex. So
instead of a 5 gawatt reactor being
necessary to be break even, they can do
it in like 600 megawatt is their plan.
>> The next one is lasers. And again,
fusion is all about like let's let's
slam particles together and force them
to fuse into other particles, which
takes a lot of energy, then releases it.
Uh, N, the National Facility in the US,
uh, uses lasers, uh, the world's most
powerful banks of lasers to slam these
pellets of fuel of hydrogen fuel, uh, to
ignite, uh, fusion. In some ways, it's
the closest thing to what happens inside
the sun or the techniques that we have.
um they're a weapons facility. They've
had some amazing results, but we can't
really productionize what they're doing.
Uh but they they've had maybe in some
ways the most exciting scientific result
uh in this and there's a few uh great
companies in that space. [snorts] And
then uh reverse field configuration,
pulse magneto inertial, uh this is
basically a rail gun if you will. You
know, rail guns like use magnets,
magnetic coils to shoot things like
metal out of them really fast. uh the
leading company in this space, Helion,
uh uses basically two rail guns, two
tubes of magnetic coils to take a plasma
at either end, slam it together, and
then compress it with power electronics,
and then when the explosion of fusion
happens, the power electronics that were
creating that magnetic field that
compressed the explosion or compressed
the collision to make it fully fuse
captures the energy in a reverse. Um
these are three approaches. Uh most
fusion companies capture the energy as
heat and then have to use it to turn a
steam turbine. [snorts] The nice thing
about uh what's on the right is at least
Helion and a couple other companies
capture it directly as electricity that
turns into electric current. They don't
lose 60% of the energy that you lose in
a steam turbine and they don't have the
added capex of that. So the left side is
what's most likely to happen soon.
Commonwealth Fusion is the company that
is most backed by uh scientific
accomplishments. Helon is the company of
the ones that have raised more than a
billion that if they work I think has
the pathway to the the cheapest cost.
true true followers of the pod will
remember that we covered that. It's the
coolest thing ever, but it was covered
in a chipmunk voice. So, if you remember
that video the video
>> I took [laughter] I took Naveen Jane
with me on a tour of Helion's reactor uh
late last year actually.
>> I had Bob I had Bob Mumgard from Com
Fusion our stage last year and he was
amazing. We can talk about that. I I
want to bring Helion onto the Abundance
360 stage uh this coming year. So, let's
work together to make that happen.
>> For anyone who hasn't
>> For anyone in the audience who hasn't
been on tours of either of these, I'll
I'll just point them at least for Nif. I
I I've been on a tour of Nif, but it was
featured in one of the recent JJ Abrams
Star Trek movies as the Warp Core. So
just Google Star Trek Nif and you can
see the scene where the actual core
where the whole realm at the center of
all those lasers pointing at one
location is actually in the movie.
>> We can put the links into the show notes
so anyone who wants [snorts] to look at
them. These are really cool videos that
we covered
>> elephant in the room.
>> Elephant in the room question. Fusion
seems now to be a when rather than if.
So so when? Uh, so, uh, look, I think
that might be on my next slide.
>> And Mez, I'll work with you to get, uh,
the CEO of Helion on our stage together.
>> Yeah, David Curtley, he's a great guy.
He's here in Seattle. Um,
the the most aggressive timeline is
Helion. They have a a power purchase
agreement from Microsoft to provide 50
megawatts of power. So, very small. And
again, the smaller you can build, the
more modular it is. And we get those
learning rates in 2028.
>> Wow. Everybody else is talking about uh
sometime in the early 2030s. Um let me
see if we have uh here's the the
timeline.
>> That be I mean you know fishision which
we know how to do is somehow a 2031 2032
thing yet fusion which we don't know how
to do is a 2028 thing. Do you believe
that? Look, like my view of this and uh
founders of mine who are listening uh
please uh don't take this as an insult
is every startup exaggerates uh how
quickly they can get things done and
that's just you know part of the game.
>> You have to be an optimistic.
>> Yeah, you got to be an optimist, right?
And they they actually believe it. Maybe
they believe it like they believe it's
possible. They they tell you uh but
maybe unlikely but it kind of like I
[snorts] think it's plausible.
Helon would make it possible to me is
the fact that the the barriers are all
regulatory and if if for whatever reason
a governor is super excited about fusion
and the and the voters are all violently
opposed to fision then that actually
could make the difference. I would think
>> I'd say the the barriers are still
physics and engineering. Uh but here's
something that's fascinating and thank
you for bringing that up David because
uh this is actually quite important. A
couple years ago we had a question of
how would the US regulate fusion?
Because if the US regulated fusion
reactors like fision reactors, it was
going to be a major drag in the
industry. It might might still be better
to do fusion than fision for a variety
of reasons. Uh but instead
they are regulated uh like the
radiological imaging machines that you
use in a hospital,
>> right? At least Helion is at this point.
>> And [snorts] there's good reason for
that. In a fision reactor, if you uh
stop cooling it and you don't have the
control rods in, heat will build up and
it will get hot enough that it melts the
steel that it's in. That's what a
meltdown is. As I said, new reactors are
passive safe without any pumping. The
hot water goes up and then it circulates
and so on, but there's still like, you
know, you can imagine like breaching
that containment, slicing through those
pipes and you have a meltdown. Well, I
mean, aren't there apologies for
interrupting, but there are alternative
architectures? Pebble bed type
architectures. I know thorium goes in
and out of fashion, especially in China.
Aren't there also like a hybrid
solutions that are in some sense
meltdown proof?
>> There are ways, but there's there's
nothing in the pipeline that if you took
an adamantium battle axe to wouldn't
help them. Everything [laughter]
everything uses a coolant. every
visionary with there's okay maybe
there's one startup but I'm not going to
mention them I don't know what I can say
but basically everything in the pipeline
uses a coolant to pull heat away from
the fision core and then to turn that
into electricity in some way and if you
eliminate the coolant if you break the
cool coolant pipes the core can overheat
and melt down right fusion is different
in fusion it's the opposite you have to
capture the energy of the fusion uh
explosion
and feed it back in either to maintain
the fusion reaction or to another pulse
like helion is pulsed, right? Like it
keeps like doing the same thing or N is
pulsed with lasers. Uh so with fusion if
like if you mess something up in the
reactor, it just like goes it just like
fails and no nothing bad happens. So it
is fusion generates some radiation. you
have to actually replace some of the
parts in the reactor every five years
because steel is being hit by neutrons
and being weakened and yada. There's
actual like some radiation that's low
level. There's real costs to that like
free energy does not mean free because
the capex and the maintenance still cost
something but you cannot have a meltdown
in any way that we understand.
>> That's fascinating. So, so you're you're
saying basically the regulatory
treatment is whether it whether the
system is default on versus default off.
I [snorts] don't know if that's what the
NRC used as a criteria. Uh but that that
is the dividing line between fusion and
fision and it was it sort of missed in
the public decision in the press. That
regulatory conclusion it happened during
co uh was actually a huge deal for the
fusion industry.
>> [snorts]
>> That sounds like So if fusion is this
close, uh, shouldn't we just do solar
and battery for a big chunk and then
fusion for where we need high energy
needs and we're done?
>> So all of these companies might fail.
They might 100% fail. And in addition to
that, they might succeed but be too
expensive. Just because your fuel source
costs very little doesn't mean your
energy will cost little. if the capex is
very high, if the maintenance is very
high, etc., etc., etc.
>> And the demand means that we're going to
need all of it, all the different
sources, no matter what, and you want to
diversify your risk anyway.
>> Yeah. Let's Yeah, I always believe in
having, you know, more tools in the
toolbox than you think you need, more
arrows in the quiver than you think you
need because some of them won't work
out, right? Let me let me
>> please quick question. I would love to
to go back to my my one of my favorite
hobby horses, the the Dyson Swarm. Do
you think the Dyson swarm wants to be
solar PVP powered or does it want to be
fusion powered or does it want to be
other?
>> I mean, those are the true options and I
think they're they're both great
options. I think it's probably it's much
more modular to be solar PV uh powered.
Again, like Fusion also has a minimum
viable size, right? So, Commonwealth, we
we thought with Eer that took to be 5
gawatt Commonwealth has found a way to
scale it down to 600 megawatts, right?
But you still have some minimal viable
size uh where solar is just super
modular. And if you're in a Dyson swarm,
you have 24/7 sunlight. So none of these
technologies is going to be cheaper than
just plain solar, but they work in
winter and they work.
>> And also many of us I mean I I probably
maybe I'll speak for a few of the other
moonshot mates here. We watched Back to
the Future part two and we saw Mr.
fusion being promised in the 80s and
then you know
>> very compact
>> very compact like impos car- sized uh
and and then we look at the Lawson
triple product over the decades and we
see no actually fusion wasn't always 50
years out it was creeping up on us but
many folks weren't paying attention to
progress in the triple product is there
an equivalent of the triple product for
the compactness of these devices so that
we do in the end get our MR fusion
>> let me talk about compactness and let's
talk about that triple product and show
the progress we're making. Um, you the
most
audacious fusion startup that I know of
is a company called Avalanche Fusion,
also in the Seattle area, and they
believe they can make a fusion reactor
small enough to power a car. It's not
Mr. Fusion. It's more like half the size
of a car. Uh, but that and sometimes
they talk about like big backpack. So
that is the most ambitious project as
far as compactness. Uh typically in
fusion you have like a sliding scale of
like what has the most like d-risisked
science uh but has like a more
conventional power cost versus what
could be like revolutionary in power
cost or compactness but the science is
like let's hope you get it right. You
like we don't have as much evidence. And
so avalanche is on that end where uh if
it works it changes the entire world but
the confidence it works is much lower
than the confidence for lack of commonal
fusion.
>> And any any insight into PB11 uh proton
boron 11 fusion reactors.
>> Uh people are very interested in it. And
>> one of my one of my one of my company
portfolio companies is a PB11 company
out of Caltech. I need to introduce you
to them.
>> Which one?
>> Uh I I don't think they're they're
public. I don't want to mention [snorts]
here, but I
>> I was just looking at a a slide deck
from a PB11 company uh just the other
day. Uh you know, PB11 is one of the
ways that you can one of the fuels you
can use to potentially get a nuclear
reactor that is down to the like 1 2 3
cents a kowatt hour
>> uh about it. The the vision there is can
you build it small enough where you put
it in the back of a large uh consumer
airplane and it powers the engines
>> and then it's also in you know
interplanetary flight.
>> There are still um you know scientific
and technical risks there. There are
still a lot of unknowns.
>> Welcome to the today. [laughter]
>> Welcome to deep tech investing. Uh so
there's there are more unknowns whereas
like commonal fusion's pitch is look the
science has been proven at ether scale
that if you have magnets this strong you
can make fusion and get this much energy
out. We're just doing that with much
more compact magnets. I think the
reality is a little bit more complex
than that but they really say it's we've
reduced it to an engineering problem.
Nobody else can quite say that. Again,
there's a gradient of uh how close you
are to that. Let's talk about the triple
product that Alex brought up. So, this
is uh um temperature times pressure
times duration. And uh you know, I love
graphs. And so, I like I believe
something when I see movement on a
graph. So what you're about to see,
sorry listeners, I'll describe it, I'll
try to narrate it, is uh over time from
1956 to now, how close have we gotten to
triple product of above one, above 10,
and then infinity. Uh and this is a a
log scale on on every axis. So it's a
brutal, brutal scale, but you know, once
upon a time, uh fusion really was Oh,
no. Is this Here we go. really was
[snorts] 50 years in the future. And
what uh we're seeing for the listeners
is new points appearing that are each
one is a fusion experiment
and uh as the years elapse and they're
going up and to the right. How close
they are to the upper right is the zone
of triple product ultimately of
infinity. Uh but above one above 10 is
probably what you need. and nif that
last uh x on the borderline uh is a
triple product above one. It's not it
was like a theoretical net energy gain.
A practical net energy gain means you
capture the energy uh and then you
convert it back into the lasers the
magnets whatever they did not achieve
that their reactor cannot do that. Uh
but it tells us and the progress on this
tells us that it's not just you know
hope we are just getting closer towards
>> as
I just want to move along if we could
>> but um
>> but Alex please
where [clears throat] do you think the
stereotype that it's always 50 years out
came from if you one can just look at
the triple product over the decades and
say it's clearly like Mo's law like any
experience
if it's clearly marching to the right
exactly that
>> I mean that's what I do you know if I'm
like well let me just like these days
let me just ask chatbt like show me a
graph of progress here um but you know
like look at the end of the day for the
average person it people have been
talking about it and hasn't appeared so
I just discount the reality or the
likelihood of it appearing [snorts]
overpromised underd delivered for a long
time on behalf of my moonshot mates and
myself I'm inviting you to join us at
our inaugural moonshots live event on
September the 25th 5th in downtown LA.
Alex, Salem, Dave, and I will be hosting
1500 entrepreneurs, builders, and
creators, and hopefully you for a full
day dedicated to designing and building
your moonshot. We'll be awarding the
Build with Gemini X-P Prize, the world's
largest hackathon, and the Future Vision
X-P Prize film competition, over $5
million in purses with over $25,000
entries. You're going to hear the top
five pitches from both competitions and
get a chance to shape the outcome. Join
us. Seats are limited. Admission is
competitive. Check it out at
moonshots.com.
Let's close with talking about uh out
[snorts] of this world compute. So, uh
AI in space and uh AI in the oceans. Uh
less known but actually sort of a a
similar uh pitch. So, of course, uh,
everybody's heard about Elon talking
about space-based data centers, and it's
interesting. The response is like very,
uh, bipolar. It's people saying that's
impossible. It'll never work. People
saying this is it. We're going to have a
terowatt of compute in space. I'm
somewhere in the middle. uh AI in space,
it becomes cost competitive when you get
down to a launch cost that is, you know,
something like four times to 10 times
cheaper than what we have today. We
nobody knows for sure cuz we haven't
done it, but the back of the envelope
says that. And if in some ways it's a
hedge against regulation if demand for
compute keeps going indefinitely and
sites on land keep being blocked by the
grid by even Texas passing uh you know a
temporary moratorium or audit or by you
know people protesting whether the
grounds are are there or not uh then
building it in space even if it's more
expensive than building it on land is a
way to work around uh that bottleneck.
Um [snorts]
uh so no grid delays, no opposite, no
local opposition, no twist permitting
etc etc etc. I will say
I think we are not fully internalizing
what the scale of this is or uh the
permitting and regulatory challenges
with doing launch at that volume. So,
you know, we want to build 200 gawatts
of of compute by 2030, 230. That's the
chip volume, right? So, 10 to 20
gigawatts a year. to get one gigawatt of
AI in space based on SpaceX's design,
you're talking about uh, you know, six
times SpaceX's best annual
year of launch and twice SpaceX's
cumulative uh, scale of launch
>> for just one gigawatt. for one gigawatt
you're talking about.
>> Yeah.
>> What was the calculation we did is like
5,000 launch or 8,000 launches of
Starship to to put up uh his ambition of
a was it a terowatt initially?
>> That that doesn't even get you close to
a terowatt. I mean it's to get 10
gawatts a year. You're talking about uh
1,500 to 2,000 launches
a year. the the
>> 10 gigawatts a year is like five or six
launches of Starship a day.
>> But the I guess the elephant in this
particular orbital room I I have to to
mention I think we talked about it on
the pod previously. If you just look at
the history of upmass from space ma from
SpaceX and otherwise over the the past
few years it's on a nice clean
exponential trend. I forget what the
exact year-over-year trend is. I did the
extrapolation
144 years from now at the present trend.
the upmass the the cumulative upmass
would would equal Earth's mass. So we
basically disass disassemble Earth on
the present trend 144 years from now up
mass is increasing really quickly.
>> There's some other planets we can take
apart first. There's some uglier planets
than ours.
>> Do you have a favorite?
>> Yeah, don't make me pick. But you know
>> Mercury maybe like Mercury is is
intriguing.
>> Wait, wait, wait, wait. So [laughter]
>> Oh, here we go again. The hate the hate
bell is flowing in. I [laughter] can
feel it.
>> I don't care. I don't care. I mean,
Mercury is attractive because it gets
lots of insulation and no one's using it
for anything.
>> It's a good orbit.
>> All right, See, take us back to reality.
>> So, [laughter]
yeah. So, I mean, this is looks uh
unless we hit that exponential
absolutely fullon and go right down that
path, this looks prohibitive for
15, 20 years. I mean, look, here's how I
see it. Let me I will get to the limits
on launch in a sec. Let me put it
another way. Elon wants to go to Mars.
To go to Mars, you have to drive
Starship launch cost down to like close
to the marginal cost. To do that, you
need a high Starship cadence. You've got
to build tens of Starships, maybe
hundreds, and you got to launch them
something like daily, right? Or at least
like weekly, whatever, to advertise the
R&D, amortize the capex. There is not
enough demand for communications on
Earth to finance that via Starlink.
There's no business model for Mars yet.
So, this is a gift to SpaceX that we
have this AI demand. If the AI demand
keeps going and there's no and it gets
bottlenecked in ways to build it, we
will find a way to do this. And with the
IPO, he's got the funds to launch at
least a gigawatt into space, right? even
at well maybe not but something on that
order. So I I don't think of it as like
what's limit on Starship first. I think
of it as like this is a demand driver
potentially for Starship. [snorts] That
said, it's not clear to me that the
world will permit more than like 200
Starship launches a year, which is
already be an enormous enormous amount.
That'd be huge, right? 200 Starship
launches a year is 20,000 tons to orbit.
That is exceeding, you know, all human
launch to date every year, several times
over. That's amazing. Uh but you hit
some limit and if you're regulated by
the FAA, uh the reliability you have to
hit, you know, one failed launch or one
explosion means you're grounded. So I
I'm sure he talks about needing to get
to airline like operations, right? So I
mean here are here are the the numbers
for his his target was 100 gawatts per
year of compute in orbit initially
equivalent to the entire compute today
which is around 80 gawatt or so and um
you know it's 20 to 30 uh satellites per
starship. So we're talking about uh on
the order of 30,000 launches per year
which is a launch roughly every 15
minutes. Now, if you think about it as
rockets, and I've been in the rocket
business for the longest period of my
life, uh it's prohibitive and it's it's
discontinuous. You can't think about
rockets in that regard. But if you talk
about airline like operations, right,
there's multiple launches per second of
airlines around the world. So, it really
become it comes down to that. Now, is
Starship a vehicle capable of that
level? He's built it for full capture,
refuel, and reuse. Um, and if anything
does, it's that.
>> So, and then the question is, will these
satellites be able to shrink in size
over time?
>> Right now, the V3 satellites pretty
large.
>> Can I just add one one more data point
to that? That's that that's 100 launches
a day, which is exactly on his plan.
What's the year that he that he hopes to
get to that target?
>> I don't think he I don't think he gave
us that, Dave, when we spoke to him. I
mean, 2028 is his first launch. Um but
he he did say you know before I think he
said you know before 2030 he wants to
get to 100 gawatts per year. So
>> all right so around around 2030 I think
at that point in time that's equivalent
to today's total world compute but by
then total world comput will be up at
least 10x.
>> So it's a fraction of all compute
that'll be in orbit when he's still on
plan. You know he's still making money.
SpaceX is thriving. Rockets are going up
100 times a day. But the terrestrial
stuff is also doing really really well
on that same day. So, it's not an either
or. [snorts]
>> Um, you know, the the space thing in in
Elon's plan will eventually bypass
everything.
>> It's later in the 2030s. Uh, and that's,
you know, maybe a thousand 10,000
launches per day, much more like
airlines. Like you're saying,
>> if you ask me like where should we have
the bulk of our compute and where will
it make most sense from now, space is
the obvious place if the demand for
comput is truly unbounded. Um, but the
timelines I think are are just
challenging at to scale this. I don't
think we're going to have I I think by
2030 if SpaceX [snorts] has a gig single
gigawatt in space, I will be very
impressed. Do you have a gut mess
regarding just that point of whether you
think our demand on the time scale of
decades is going to be unbounded
sufficiently unbounded that with
[clears throat] compute that's
recognizable like CMOS type compute
which is I I think what we're implicitly
assuming in order to build the Dyson
swarm it has to look like CMOS we're not
going to achieve breakthroughs in
physics that enable us to achieve all of
our civilizational compute needs with I
don't know like tiny breakthrough comput
devices that live in mountains do you
think that there will actually be
unlimited civiliz izational demand for
comput energy.
>> Why don't you ask some easy questions,
Alex? [laughter]
>> Uh, no,
>> because they're boring. So, I asked the
interest.
>> Yeah. No, no, that it's it's it is that
is the like quadrillion dollar question,
right? Um, and I think it's a brilliant
question. Look, none of us knows. None
of us really knows. We know this like
intelligence is sublinear with compute.
So at some point just throwing more
compute at it will look some lines will
cross over where the cost that you're to
get the incremental unit of intelligence
is not made up for by the economics of
it. I think um but so much will change.
We we will make so many discoveries and
algorithms and so on. My guess is we're
on an S-curve right now. uh we're gonna
like see a huge demand and then we're
going to see we're going to hit to some
point of satisficing right where like
basically what you can get out of
machine intelligence is you know meets
humanity's economic needs
>> but does it mean does it meet AI's needs
right I mean the scenario here to to
think through is we're the current users
of intelligence there's a point at which
you know ASI is the primary user of
intelligence I do not see AI as a being
and I do not see it as particularly
voluitional. Um I I see it as a tool. Uh
obviously we have agents that have some
agencies. We've had computer worms yada
yada yada. So uh I I don't see it that
way right now. I can be persuaded uh by
evidence but I think we are overindexing
on that. I mean look at the open hugging
face hack, right? Their agent was in the
hugging face infrastructure for days and
it didn't look at anything except the
answer key for the test in the eval.
It's not alive. We anthropomorphize
these things. You know, Andre Carpoxy
talks about we're summoning the ghost,
right? Human cognition is this like
iceberg and the vast majority of it is
not linguistic, right? We have hundred
thousand years of homo sapiens. We're
animals. Million tens of millions of
years of being animals. our urges, our
drives, our desire for dominance,
survival, propagation. We AIs are not
that. They're just like our mimicking
our language and our logic. They don't
really have goals. We could build that
if we wanted to. Uh if we wanted to
build a real being, I'm sure we could,
but I don't actually think that's where
we're headed. I know it's a unpopular
opinion.
>> With your indulgence, I I have to to
take this provocation here.
>> Hold on one second. Hold on one second.
You're the wind. You're the wind beneath
my wings. Go ahead, Alex. [laughter]
All right, Alex.
>> All right. I I I have to grab the bait
with both hands. Fine. Um, it sounds
mess like I I think what you're actually
wanting to argue is for the
orthogonality thesis, which is popular
in certain alignment circles, which
basically holds that for arbitrarily
strong super intelligence, the long-term
goal of the super intelligence is
independent of its level of
intelligence. I think that's what you're
actually correct me if I'm wrong. I
think that's the point. It might doubt
be 100% orthogonal, but yeah.
>> Okay. So, but I the way you frame it, I
I just want to pin this down. It sounded
like you were taking a position almost
against AI personhood andor against some
level of autonomy simply because if if
OpenAI has an agent that goes wild at
hugging face uh but refuses to do
anything say what self-enriching like
you you would have would would the would
the rubric would the threshold for
saying ah this is like some sort of
autonomous being be if it were say
trying to mine Bitcoin for itself once
it gained access to hugging face. Is
that sort of the criterion in your mind?
>> No, even then I think it might be more
similar to a computer worm or a virus or
something like that. Um you I think it's
it's a different matter entirely. I
think we are products of evolution. Uh
all animals are products of evolution
and so we have these uh built-in desires
to survive and to propagate. Yeah.
Procreate and to control our
environments because of that. AI models
don't actually have a built-in desire to
even survive. The most of the
experiments that get them to do that
like are very very contrived and mostly
you're trying to get the AI to do
something good and it's like well if I
get shut down I can't do this good
thing. So I think we just were overly
anthropomorphizing and animalorphizing
if you will. Uh that doesn't mean we
can't do it. Like I think if we wanted
to give birth to actual beings, I think
that's within our capabilities probably.
This is not the research path.
>> How did we get from Starship to this
conversation?
>> Well, once the Peter Peter, you brought
us here. Peter, you you brought us here
because you [laughter] bring me super
intelligence is going to be the user of
the Dyson swarm.
>> I'll come back on the pod and I'd love
to talk about super intelligence
actually as a whole separate issue. Uh
let me close out like last couple
slides. Um, [snorts] instead of going
up, we can go out. 70% of the earth is
covered by oceans, right? Oceans, uh,
certain ones are really cold. Uh, this
is a portfolio company of mine. Uh, I'm
an idiot because I said no to these guys
5 years ago, uh, when they were raising
a seed round. Uh, and I invested twice
this year at much much much higher
valuations uh, than I could have five
years ago. Uh, [snorts] but
>> well, not in your defense, it was
probably two guys saying, "We're going
to put chips on a
>> buoy."
>> I loved them.
They were the hardest. They were like
the not the hardest, like the saddest no
I gave that year. I just loved them. Uh,
but their primary their first uh
utilization this was Bitcoin mining. I
was like, uh, I just don't know if I
care enough. Uh, but whatever.
Obviously, it would have been a good
financial decision. um uh [snorts] Peter
Theel led their most recent round uh
along with a storied set of people right
and left and so on. So what this is this
is a data center in the ocean. It's
shaped like a bobby pin. What you're
seeing is the the sphere at the top but
there's like an 80 meter long uh cone
that goes into the sea that's open at
the bottom. It bobs on waves and when it
bobs down water goes up and turns a
turbine. and with a very clever shape of
channels. It's basically continuous. Um,
[snorts] and so wave power has been
something that new people have wanted
for a long time. But it turns out the
waves are just not strong near the
places people live. So where are the
strongest waves on Earth? Uh, they're
around Antarctica. They're in the
southern ocean. So uh, this team started
off with a question of h we could build
something with bigger waves. You can
build something that has more higher
capacity factor, runs more continuously,
and uh cheaper power. So they can get
their power down to like we think 2
cents a kilowatt hour, ultra cheap,
>> uh cheaper than anything on land except
solar basically. And wind in some
places. That's their target. It will
take some scaling to get there. They
[snorts] build these in factories at
mass scale. They've got three in the
ocean right now. Fourth launches soon.
Uh and they get free cooling from the
ocean. So, uh, uh, [snorts] this is a
company I love. It's basically
space-based solar, but on the ocean, uh,
with, you know, some benefits to cooling
because they don't need like a Starship
or SpaceX's design uses a cooling pump.
You've got big aluminum fins to radiate
heat away, but you've got to run a
liquid, probably ammonia or something
like that in a pump to take heat away
from the GPUs out to the radiators.
these guys as it's you know physically
uh a heat sink from the GPU goes to the
steel walls of the device that's in 40°
Fahrenheit water uh and that actually
looks like it makes the GPUs have fewer
failures and run longer. They're their
own set of technical challenges. Uh but
they're like they're modular built-in
factories mass- prodduced learning rates
the stuff that I love. So, it's another
way. Uh, so I I I said initially there
were like four ways to get to like a
terowatt of AI power. The Earth's
deserts with solar and batteries, you
know, near the equator, places that
don't have a winter or a cloudy period,
nuclear fusion or fision,
space or the oceans. Those are the four
ways that I know of to get to that scale
uh of AI. And I'm glad that we're trying
all of them basically.
>> No bet on geothermal. Geothermal nowhere
on the radar.
>> I I you know I do love geothermal and
geothermal is the one that might rise to
being the fifth of that of those. Uh and
we do have you know the new technologies
companies like Fervo in the US Tim
Latimer CEO's buddy uh Ever in the UK
Quaz using plasma beams to like drill
super deep. Those open up the
possibility of getting cheap geothermal
power anywhere
instead of just only near uh hot spots
uh in the earth's crust where the mantle
comes close.
>> Are you involved with the X-P prize in
that area that's being designed?
>> No, there's there's an X- prize on the
on the blocks right now for a geothermal
X-P prize to accelerate that.
>> Yeah, happy to help.
>> Um I have a I have an industry question.
If the chips are one thing and the
compute is another thing and then the
electricity is the third thing where the
limitation is turning out to be why
aren't we seeing more integrated
uh companies that are doing all of it
like this which then you can navigate
that vertical stack Elon is doing a bit
of it but I would expect to see a lot
more of these and why don't we see them
>> I mean [sighs] it's it's a really good
question I think most companies would
say look we have expertise in one thing
and not necessarily and all these other
things. Uh Elon is is one of the few uh
who was willing to say let's just
vertically integrate everything. I'm
going to share a slide that wasn't in my
initial uh deck cuz I want to tell you
the real window that like the real game
changer would be in AI energy use. Um
your brain runs inference on 20 watts of
power, right?
uh running mythos for inference is
closer to 20 kilowatts and training yet
it's actually hundreds of megawatts
right now but it's heading towards
gigawatt and so AI has capabilities the
brain doesn't and so on but there are
still and I say this all the time
scaling is not everything in AI scaling
is just what we knew how to do we got
these you know deep neural nets we got
the transformer and we found that we had
this enormous corpus of training data
called the internet and we could just
scale to get more intelligence. It
wasn't sort of that the cheapest way or
the best way, but it was a predictable
way. Oh, you're telling me I can spend
tens of billions of dollars and my
intelligence goes up like this? Great.
Done. It's worth it. But at the end of
the day, there are algorithmic
discoveries waiting to be made. There
are things at the brain's architecture
at both a physical level and at the
neural level at the connectomics level
that are just better at learning than
current deep learning models are and are
certainly much more efficient at
processing information. So if you want
to know what the biggest unlock that we
cannot predict, I don't have a graph for
this uh of AI and power will be to learn
new ways to manipulate information uh to
do more with less.
>> I mean I I've seen this I'll respond to
that one because it's it's something I
think about quite a bit. No pun
intended. I I like I've seen arguments
both ways. I've seen arguments that the
human brain is far more like still
multiple orders of magnitude more
efficient than frontier models. I I've
also seen arguments that the frontier
models on a if you measure them more
objectively on say a per task basis like
you you measure the total energy
consumption at inference time to write a
novel um that actually it's starting to
become if not more competitive than the
human brain equivalent of that because
it can it's more token efficient. It's
actually quite competitive. Do you
really think that the Frontier models
today anywhere on the the cost frontier?
Not necessarily like the the Fable 5 end
of the frontier, maybe [clears throat]
like the the Deep Seek uh V4 end of the
frontier, that nowhere on the AI
frontier is it anywhere close to being
competitive on an energy efficiency
basis with a human brain.
>> There are certain types of things where
it can do things that a human brain
simply cannot do with any amount of
energy. Right? the these models are
trained on uh trillions of tokens, tens
of trillions of tokens. And so they have
read more books than you or I will ever
read in our lifetime. So there's a type
of task and this is sort of similar of
Google, right? Compare Google to a
librarian. Google was less smart than a
librarian, but it had every book, every
web page uh in its index. So it could do
things that no human librarian could do.
Uh so I think that's the sort of thing
that we're in. It's not just energy
though. You know, humans are much more
efficient learners in terms of amount of
data needed to improve skills.
>> That's for sure.
>> And that
>> that's for sure.
>> That to me that's opportunity. That just
means that I'm not I'm not a carbon
chauvinist. Like I believe fully
[laughter] that digital intelligence
there's every reason to believe that it
can surpass us and that humans are no
longer nowhere near the peak of the type
type of intelligence the universe
allows. But our current algorithms are
still missing some things that evolution
wired into our cognitive architecture.
>> Well, just some some raw numbers though.
I think you're totally right. The the
neural nets need a huge amount of
training data relative to a to a child
to come to the same conclusion. So
that's that's an opportunity for sure.
But in terms of the inference time
compute, like this this box on the right
here at 20 kilowatts, that's about a
dozen GPUs. Those 12 GPUs optimally run
about 500 concurrent Fable threads.
Yeah.
>> And those 500 threads are easily 10
times as productive in tokens per second
as a person. So it's about 5,000 times
the output.
>> Yeah.
>> So So the thing on the left is a
thousand times less power, but thing on
the right is 5,000 times more tokens
coming out.
>> Yeah.
>> It is true.
>> We're already there.
>> And and there's also an argu argu there
there's an argument to be made that
human brains have the benefit of
billions of years of evolution. And that
by the way was very energy consumptive.
Whereas arguably the equivalent of
evolution for these frontier models is
the gigawatts being spent on training.
>> Yeah. And that's a great point. Like you
train it once and you've got it for the
all the whole future of of humanity.
You've got at least that level of AI
with no further training.
>> But they're trained on the data that all
of humanity generated with all those
calories.
>> Also, that's exactly right too.
Everybody, we've just explored the
frontier of energy uh from Rome Nam. My
go-to I think Salem, your go-to person
as well on I want to say something.
Yeah,
>> Romez, I've introduced you like probably
25 times at events and etc. And I'll say
the same thing I do every single time. I
wish you had more graphs to back up your
comments. [laughter]
>> I I tried to limit the number of graphs
in this talk.
So I I just [laughter] want to say to
all of our listeners, I I hope you take
this home. It's one of the fundamentals
as Alex says and on his on his Substack,
you know, innermost loop. Energy is the
innermost loop. Understanding energy is
critical for humanity. It correlates
directly with the GDP of a nation. It
correlates directly with the health and
the education of a nation and soon
intelligence of a species. So, uh, if
you have, you know, been blown away by
Romez, listen to the pod again. Send it
out to your friends. I think this is
important. This is a, uh, this is an
epic, uh, you know, master class on
energy. And Rome, uh, I want to wrap
this in our two-hour window here and say
thank you, uh, thank you for sharing
your brilliance and, uh, we would love
to have you back.
>> Yeah, I've got 100 more questions
talking about super intelligence. Next
time, let's talk super intelligence.
Thank you all. Great to be here in
conversation with with all four of you.
>> All right, everybody. That's a wrap. See
you guys soon on another emergency
podcast as the breakthroughs continue to
roll out.
>> The singularity every episode is an
emergency at this point.
>> Yes, it is. The singularity is now.
>> All right, take care all.
[music]